[

    {
        "question": "1. Fill in the blank. Buddhist missionaries from China introduced hand printing technology into around A.D. 768-",
        "answer": "1. Buddhist missionaries from China introduced hand- printing technology into Japan around A.D. 768-"
    },
    {
        "question": "2. Name the oldest Japanese book. (2020 C, 2016) R",
        "answer": "2. Diamond Sutra"
    },
    {
        "question": "3. Explain the meaning of the term 'Calligraphy. (AI 2019, 2014)",
        "answer": "3. Calligraphy is a visual art of giving form to signs and writing or lettering in an expressive, harmonious, and skillful manner with a pen or brush."
    },
    {
        "question": "4. Who introduced hand-printing technology in Japan? (2014)",
        "answer": "4. Buddhist missionaries from China."
    },
    {
        "question": "5. Which method of hand-printing was developed in China? (2014) SAI (3 marks)",
        "answer": "5. Woodblock printing"
    },
    {
        "question": "6. How had the Imperial State in China been the major producer of printed material for a long time? Explain with examples. (Delhi 2019)",
        "answer": "6. The Imperial state in China for a long time was the major producer of printed material. China had a large bureaucracy. The Chinese civil services examinations required the use of large number of text books for its preparation in the recruitment process. Thus, large number of books and other study materials were printed under the sponsorship of the Imperial state. From the 16th century, the number of examination candidates went up and thus the volume of print also increased. Thus, printing of books started rapidly all over the nation. This was further accelerated by authors and rich merchants."
    },
    {
        "question": "7. Describe any five uses of print culture in the 17th century China. (2014)",
        "answer": "7. (i) By the 17th century, as urban culture bloomed in China, the uses of print diversified. (ii) Print was no longer used just by scholar-officials. (iii) Merchants used print in their everyday life, as they collected trade information. (iv) The new readership preferred fictional narratives, poetry, autobiographies, anthologies of literary masterpieces and romantic plays. (v) Rich women began to read and many women began publishing their poetry and plays. (vi) Wives of scholar-officials published their works and courtsmen wrote about their lives."
    },
    {
        "question": "5.2 Print Comes to Europe MCQ",
        "answer": "5. Woodblock printing"
    },
    {
        "question": "8. 'Vellum' is (a) Printing on palm leaves (b) Printing on paper (c) A parchment made from the skin of animals (d) Printing on cloth. (2020) VSA (1 mark)",
        "answer": "8. (c): A parchment made from the skin of animals"
    },
    {
        "question": "9. Who invented the Printing Press? (2020)",
        "answer": "9. Johann Gutenberg"
    },
    {
        "question": "10. Who brought the knowledge of woodblock printing technique to Italy during the 13th century? (2020)",
        "answer": "10. Marco Polo"
    },
    {
        "question": "11. By 1448, Gutenberg perfected the system of printing. The first book he printed was the (2020)",
        "answer": "11. Galley"
    },
    {
        "question": "12. Wooden or Metal frames in which types are laid and the text composed for printing was known as? (2020)",
        "answer": "12. Bible"
    },
    {
        "question": "13. Name the first book printed by Gutenberg Press. (2020 C, 2017)",
        "answer": "13. The Bible"
    },
    {
        "question": "14. Who developed the first printing press? (2014) SAI (3 marks)",
        "answer": "14. Johannes Gutenberg developed the first-known printing press in the1430s."
    },
    {
        "question": "15. Mention any three reasons for the limited circulation of manuscripts in Europe before Marco Polo introduced the printing technology. (2017)",
        "answer": "15. The circulation of manuscript remained limited because: (i) The production of handwritten manuscripts could not satisfy the ever increasing demand for books. (ii) Copying was an expensive, laborious and time- consuming business. (iii) Manuscripts were fragile, awkward to handle, and could not be carried around or read easily."
    },
    {
        "question": "16. What is manuscript? Mention any two limitations of it, during nineteenth century. (2016)",
        "answer": "16. Manuscripts are hand written records of the past, written on palm leaves or on handmade paper. Limitations of manuscripts are: (i) Pages were beautifully illustrated. (ii) Manuscripts were highly expensive but fragile. (iii) They were in various vernacular languages. (iv) They could not be read easily as the script was written in different styles."
    },
    {
        "question": "17. How had the earliest printing technology developed in the world? Explain with example. (2016)",
        "answer": "17. (i) The earliest kind of print technology was developed in China, Japan and Korea. In China woodblocks were used for hand printing. (ii) Upto the 6th century print was used only by the scholar officials but later it became common. (iii) The Buddhist missionaries introduced hand printing technology from China to Japan. (iv) It was Marco Polo, a great explorer, who brought printing knowledge of woodblock from China to Italy."
    },
    {
        "question": "18. How did print help to spread new ideas that led to the reformation in Europe? (2015)",
        "answer": "18. (i) In 1517, the religious reformer Martin Luther wrote 'Ninety Five Theses' criticising many of the practices and rituals of the Roman Catholic Church. (ii) Due to writings of Martin Luther, the church got divided and a new Protestant reformation had started. (iii) Several scholars, think that print brought about a new intellectual atmosphere and helped spread the new ideas that led to reformation."
    },
    {
        "question": "19. Explain the reasons favouring shift from hand printing to mechanical printing in China. (2015, 2014)",
        "answer": "19. The reasons favouring shift from hand printing to mechanical printing in China are: (i) Textbooks of Civil Service Examination were printed in vast numbers under the sponsorship of the imperial state. From the 16th century, the number of examination candidates went up and that increased the volume of print. (ii) By the 17th century, print was no longer used just by scholar officials, merchants used print in their everyday life, as they collected trade information. (iii) The new reading culture was accompanied by a new technology. Western printing techniques and mechanical presses were imported in China and Shanghai became the new hub of the new print culture."
    },
    {
        "question": "20. Why were manuscripts not widely used in everyday life? Give three reasons. (2014)",
        "answer": "20. Manuscripts were documents or books written by hand. They were not used widely because: (i) They could not satisfy the ever increasing demand for books. (ii) They were expensive as copying was an expensive, laborious and time consuming work. (iii) Manuscripts were fragile, awkward to handle and could not be carried around or read easily. (iv) Their circulation was limited."
    },
    {
        "question": "21. Why did Roman Catholic church impose control over publishers and book sellers? (2018)",
        "answer": "21. The Roman Catholic Church imposed control over publishers and booksellers. Because scholars and writ- ers started interpreting religious books, which everyone could read and understand. The public started question- ing the Church authorities regarding the rules and regula- tions imposed and the religious beliefs. The Church want- ed to maintain its supremacy and prevent people from questioning them, imposed control over booksellers and publishers."
    },
    {
        "question": "22. Who was Menocchio? (2016)  SAI (3 marks)",
        "answer": "22. Menocchio was a miller of 16th century in Italy. He reinterpreted the message of the Bible and formulated a view of God and creation that enraged the Catholic Church."
    },
    {
        "question": "23. \"The shift from hand printing to mechanical printing led to the print revolution in Europe'. Explain the statement with examples. (2023)",
        "answer": "23. With the invention of printing press, the printing of books started on a large scale. (i) Wider sections of people started having an easy access of books. (ii) Books were printed in large numbers with greater ease. (iii) The hearing public and reading public became intermingled. (iv) Publishers started publishing popular ballads folk tales with beautiful pictures and illustrations. (v) Luther's translation of the New Testament sold 5,000 copies within a few weeks and a second edition appeared within three months. Deeply grateful to print, Luther said, 'Printing is the ultimate gift of God and the greatest one! Several scholars, in fact, think that print brought about a new intellectual atmosphere and helped spread the new ideas that led to the Reformation."
    },
    {
        "question": "24. \"Printing brought the reading public and hearing public closer.\" Substantiate the statement with appropriate argument. (2019 C)",
        "answer": "24. Access to books created a new culture of reading. Earlier, reading was restricted to the elites. Common people lived in a world of oral culture. They heard sacred texts read out, ballads recited, and folk tales narrated. Knowledge was transferred orally. People collectively heard a story, or saw a performance. They did not read a book individually and silently. Before the age of print, books were not only expensive but they could not be produced in sufficient numbers. Now books could reach out to wider sections of people. If earlier there was a hearing public, now a reading public came into being."
    },
    {
        "question": "25. \"Print Revolution in sixteenth century Europe transformed the lives of people. Support the statement with suitable arguments. (AI 2019) OR \"The Print Revolution had transformed the lives of people changing their relationship to information and knowledge\" Analyse the statement. (2018, Al 2014)",
        "answer": "25. The print revolution transformed the lives of a large section of the society in the 16th century Europe. (1) A new reading public emerged as printing reduced the cost of books making it very affordable. (ii) Access to books created a new culture of reading. Earlier, reading was restricted to the elites. Common people lived in a world of oral culture. Common folk only heard sacred texts that was read out. Knowledge was transferred orally. People collectively heard a story, or saw a performance. (iii) Now books could reach out to wider sections of people and a reading public came into being. The line that separated the oral and reading cultures became blurred. And the hearing public and reading public became intermingled."
    },
    {
        "question": "26. How did a new reading public emerge with the printing press? Explain. (2016) OR \"With the printing press a new public emerged in Europe! Justify the statement. (2015)",
        "answer": "26. (i) Wider sections of people started having an easy access to books. (ii) Books were printed in large numbers with greater ease. (iii) The prices fell and they became affordable for large public. (iv) The hearing public and reading public became intermingled."
    },
    {
        "question": "27. Why did the Roman Catholic Church begin to keep an index of prohibited books from the mid 16th century? (2015)",
        "answer": "27. (i) Printed religious literature stimulated a variety of interpretations of faith, even among the less educated working class in the early 16th century. (ii) Menocchio, an Italian miller, reinterpreted the Bible in a way that enraged the Roman Catholic Church. (iii) Such instances worried the Church about people reading the various interpretations of the religion and questioning the Church. (iv) Hence, it imposed severe controls over publishers and booksellers and began maintaining an index of prohibited books."
    },
    {
        "question": "28. What is meant by the print revolution? Explain its significance. (2014) LA (5 marks)",
        "answer": "28. With the invention of printing press, the printing of books started at a large scale. it was called the Print Revolution. Significance:  (i) With the printing press, a new reading public emerged. (ii) Printing reduced the cost of books. (iii) Books flooded the market, reaching out to an ever growing readership."
    },
    {
        "question": "29. Describe the impact of the print revolution in Europe during 15th and 16th century. (2017, 2016)",
        "answer": "29. Impact of the print revolution in Europe during the 15th and 16th century: (i) Printing reduced the cost of books. (ii) The time and labour required to produce each book came down, multiple copies could be produced with greater ease. (iii) Books flooded the market, reaching out to an ever- growing readership. (iv) Publishers started publishing popular ballads folk tales with beautiful pictures and illustrations. (v) Print created the possibility of wide circulation of ideas, and introduced a new world of debate and discussion. (vi) Even those who disagreed with established authorities, could now print and circulate their ideas, e.g. Martin Luther was a German monk, priest, professor and church reformer. He challenged the Church to debate his ideas. This led to division within the Church and the beginning of the Protestant Reformation. (vii) Print and popular religious literature stimulated many distinctive individual interpretations of faith even among little-educated working people."
    },
    {
        "question": "30. Martin Luther remarked \"Printing is the ultimate gift of God and the greatest one\". Explain this remark in the light of the religious reforms that took place in Europe in the 16th century. (2014)",
        "answer": "30. (i) Martin Luther wrote 'Ninety Five Theses' criticising the malpractices in the Roman Catholic Church. He posted a printed copy of it on the door of a church in Wittenberg. (ii) Luther's writing immediately became popular through printed copies and was read widely. (iii) 5000 printed copies of Luther's translation of the New Testament were sold in a week. (iv) All these led to a religious debate and marked the beginning of the Protestant Reformation. (v) Printing technology played a key role in bringing religious reforms in the 16th century. Hence Martin Luther's remarks were apt, effective and practical."
    }
]